Register of the Catherine A. Gumensky (Ekaterina Aleksandrovna Gumenskaia) Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Catherine A. Gumensky (Ekaterina Aleksandrovna Gumenskaia) papers
1913-1985
2000C84
Hoover Institution Archives
13 microfilm reels (2.2 linear feet), Boxes 13-17 are not included in the microfilms. Please contact the Museum for Russian Culture for further assistance.
Correspondence, writings, financial records, clippings, and photographs, relating mainly to Russian émigré and family affairs.
Gumensky, Catherine A., 1897-1988
Access
Collection is open for research.
Boxes 13-17 are not included on the microfilms. Please contact the Museum for Russian Culture for further assistance.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Biography
George C. Guins is best known to historians as the administrative secretary (upravliaiushchii delami) of the Siberian (later All-Russian) anti-Bolshevik government at Omsk. Privy to governmental decisions in this capacity as well as in concurrent service as deputy minister for education and foreign affairs, he described the workings of the government and the anti-Bolshevik campaign in Siberia, 1918-1920, in his published memoir, Sibir', soiuzniki i Kolchak (Peking, 1921).
Less well-known is his career as a legal philosopher, journalist, and writer and lecturer on the Soviet Union. Born in Novogeorgievsk (now Modlin, Poland) on 27 April 1887, he studied law at St. Petersburg University under the direction of the eminent jurist and legal philosopher Leon Petrazycki, obtaining his degree in 1909. Entering government service in the Resettlement Office (Pereselencheskoe upravlenie) of the Ministry of Agriculture, he continued legal studies in his spare time, obtaining an advanced degree in 1915 and remaining at St. Petersburg University as a lecturer. At this time he completed a dissertation on water rights in Central Asia.
The 1917 Revolution saw his promotion in government service to the post of chief legal counselor of the Ministry of Provisions, but following the Bolshevik coup in October, he left for Omsk, where he was drawn into service in the White government formed there the following summer. At the conclusion of the Civil War, he found himself in Harbin, China, where he served on the administration of the Chinese Eastern Railway until 1926, first as director of the chancellery and later as chief controller. At the same time, he edited and wrote for Russkoe obozrenie, published in Peking, and helped found the Harbin Law Faculty, a unique émigré institution training lawyers in China. Here he lectured almost until his departure for the United States in 1941, made necessary by Japanese pressure due to his independent position in Harbin politics. During this period he accomplished his greatest scholarly achievements in legal philosophy, with such publications as Novye idei v prave i osnovnye problemy sovremennosti (Harbin, 1931-1932), Uchenie o prave i politicheskaia ekonomiia (Harbin, 1933), Ocherki sotsial'noi filosofii (Harbin, 1936), all now bibliographic rarities.
Following his arrival in the United States, he settled in the San Francisco Bay Area, editing for a brief period the émigré newspaper Russkaia zhizn', and lecturing at the University of California at Berkeley and the Army Language School in Monterey. Not finding an application for his specialization in legal philosophy, he turned to teaching Russian and Soviet civilization, history, and law, publishing numerous articles and two books on Soviet affairs: Soviet Law and Soviet Society (The Hague, 1954) and Communism on the Decline (New York, 1956). Even after retiring from active teaching, he continued to lecture and write, served as a consultant to the Voice of America until 1964, and contributed an oral history to the UC Berkeley Regional Oral History Office's Russian émigré program. He died in September 1971.
Chronology
1897 July 14 (N.S.) Born, Kazan', Russia
1914-1917 Student, Moscow University, Moscow, Russia
1921 Married Dmitrii B. Gumensky Arrived in the United States
1925 B.A., University of California, Berkeley, California M.A., University of Southern California, Los Angeles, California
1927 Naturalized as a U.S. citizen
1932 Divorced Dmitrii B. Gumensky
1945-1952 Translator, U.S. Army, European High Command
1988 Died, Apple Valley, California
Scope and Content Note
Catherine A. Gumensky was a California artist of local note. The collection contains materials relating to her work as an artist and other biographical data, as well as her children's stories. Of particular significance is the family file, which contains a large amount of correspondence (of Catherine, her mother Neonila Platonovna Aristova, and others) with family members in the Soviet Union and other countries from the 1920s through the 1980s, as well as writings of other family members.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia.; Russians--United States.; United States.
- Biographical File, 1914-1983 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes affidavits, clippings, employment, identity and real estate records, with related correspondence, notes, scrapbook and miscellany, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Family File, 1913-1983 (Box 2-9)
  Correspondence, writings and associated matter, arranged alphabetically by name of relative and therein by physical form
- Correspondence, 1917-1985 (Box 9-10)
  Extrafamilial correspondence, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Writings, 1934-1977 (Box 10-11)
  Background materials, correspondence and writings, arranged chronologically by title
- Subject File, 1924-1981 (Box 12)
  Clippings, correspondence, notes, writings and other matter, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, 1910s-1980s (Box 13-16)
  Several hundred items, including photographs of Catherine and Dmitrii Gumensky, other family members (including most of those appearing in the FAMILY FILE), Ella Young, and miscellaneous people and places
- Financial Documents, 1948-1984 (Box 17)
  Income tax records, cancelled checks, property tax receipts, bank records, etc. Not filmed
- Recipes, undated (Box 17)
  Clippings and notes, primarily by N. P. Aristova. Not filmed
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1914-1983 (Box 1)
  General note
  For Gumensky's activities in the U.S. Army European High Command, 1945-1952, see SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/Untitled account of activities in Europe from 1945 to 1952, n.d.
  - Addresses (Folder 1: 1)
  - Affidavits of support, signed by Catherine Gumensky, to invite relatives to the U.S. (Folder 1: 2)
  - Clippings (Folder 1: 3)
  - Curriculum vitae (Folder 1: 4)
  - Employment records (Folder 1: 5)
  - Genealogical notes (Folder 1: 6)
  - Identity papers. (Folder 1: 7)
    Includes driver's license, membership cards, passes, passports, social security card, immigration papers, vaccination records, and similar matter
  - Programs (Folder 1: 8)
  - Real estate records (Folder 1: 9)
  - School records (Folder 1: 10)
  - Scrapbook (Folder 1: 11)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 1: 12-13)
    Includes notebooks with student lecture notes, jottings, sketches, impressions of life, etc., 1914-?
- FAMILY FILE, 1913-1983 (Box 2)
  Correspondence and writings of and between family members (unless otherwise indicated, entries consist exclusively of correspondence). Correspondence with Catherine may include letters addressed to Catherine and Neonila or Dimitrii. Many letters also contain postscripts by other family members, and are generally classified under the name of the first correspondent, unless the postscript is significantly longer than the original letter
  - Aleksandrova, Ekaterina Vladimirovna (niece), 1969-1983 and undated (Folder 2: 1)
  - Aleksandrova, Irina Aleksandrovna (sister), 1917-1945 (Folder 2: 2)
    Includes letters from Vladimir Aleksandrov
  - Aleksandrova, Nataliia Vladimirovna (niece), 1978-1982 (Folder 2: 3)
  - Aristova, Nadezhda (?), 1917-1923 (Folder 2: 4)
  - Aristova, Neonila Platonovna (mother)
    - Calendar, 1944 and undated (Folder 2: 5)
    - Correspondence
      - Unidentified, 1913-1943 (Folder 2: 6-8)
      - Unidentified (Box-folder 3: 1-4)
      - Aleksandrova, Irina Aleksandrovna (daughter)
        - 1928-1930 (Folder 3: 5)
        - 1931-1934 (Folder 3: 6)
        - 1935-1945 (Folder 3: 7)
      - Bubnova, Mariia, 1936-1940 (Box-folder 4: 1)
        Includes postscripts by nun Leonida, qqv., and forwarded letters from Ol'ga Platonovna Veiss (sister), qqv.
      - Butlerov, A., n.d. (Folder 4: 2)
      - Buturlin, Sofiia, 1934-1939 (Folder 4: 3)
      - Demidov, Igor Igorevich, 1939-1945 (Folder 4: 4)
      - Demidov, Igor Platonovich, 1929-1945 (Folder 4: 5)
      - Demidova (Demidoff), Ekaterina, 1930-1931 and undated (Folder 4: 6)
      - Gotlund, A. and Z., 1932-1941 and undated (Folder 4: 7)
      - Gumenskaia, Taisiia Petrovna, 1936-1945 (Folder 4: 8)
      - Gumensky, Catherine (daughter)
        - 1916-1923 and undated (Folder 4: 9)
        - 1924-1927 (Folder 4: 10)
        - 1928-1933 (Folder 4: 11)
        - 1941-1945 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - Iakunchikova (Yakounchikoff), Varvara N., 1933-1934 (Folder 5: 2)
      - Ivashnenko, A., 1932 (Folder 5: 3)
      - Kazakov (Kasakoff), A. and T., 1929-1937 and undated (Folder 5: 4)
      - Kovan'ko, Nataliia (granddaughter), 1929-1936 (Folder 5: 5)
      - Kovan'ko, Ol'ga Aleksandrovna (daughter)
        - Correspondence.
          Includes postscripts by Nataliia Kovan'ko
          - 1927-1930 (Folder 5: 6)
          - 1931-1933 (Folder 5: 7)
          - 1934-1937 (Box-folder 6: 1)
          - 1938-1945 (Folder 6: 2)
        - Sketches, "Viazovye, ", 1927 (Folder 6: 3)
      - Leonida, nun, 1929-1934 (Folder 6: 4)
        See also Bubnova, Mariia, qqv.
      - Liapunova, Anastasiia Sergeevna, 1924-1936 (Folder 6: 5)
      - Lordkipanidze-Cheptsova, Ol'ga, 1941 (Folder 6: 6)
      - Martynova, A., 1929 (Folder 6: 7)
      - Mikhnevich, Ekaterina, 1932-1934 and undated (Folder 6: 8)
      - Minchenko, Antonina Petrovna, 1934 (Folder 6: 9)
      - Panina, Sofiia Vladimirovna, 1940-1946 (Folder 6: 10)
        Includes letters addressed to Catherine Gumensky following Neonila's death in 1945
      - Razumov, Pavel, Rev., 1930-1931 (Folder 6: 11)
      - Ruhl, Zinaida, 1933 (Folder 6: 12)
      - Smieszek (Smeshek), Anton Gustavovich, 1929 (Folder 6: 13)
      - Stafford, E., 1934 (Folder 6: 14)
      - Sunitsa (Sounitza), E., 1932-1934 (Folder 6: 15)
      - Tsetlin, Mikhail Osipovich, 1945 (Folder 6: 16)
      - Vakar, Nikolai Platonovich, 1941-1945 (Folder 6: 17)
      - Veiss, Evgenii, 1929-1943 (Folder 6: 18)
      - Veiss, Ol'ga Platonovna, 1929-1936 (Folder 6: 19)
      - Wiebe, Mr., undated (Folder 6: 20)
      - Zhuravskaia, S., 1929-1937 (Folder 6: 21)
    - Log of family events from 1871 to 1917 (incomplete), n.d. (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Obituary (Folder 7: 2)
    - Passport (Folder 7: 3)
    - Writings
      - General. (Folder 7: 4)
        Notes, some of an autobiographical nature
      - "The Home of My Youth,", n.d. (Folder 7: 5)
        Holograph
      - "Iz perezhitago,", n.d. (Folder 7: 6)
        Printed copy
      - "Poiezdka k zautrenie,", n.d. (Folder 7: 7)
      - "Povar-muzykant,", n.d. (Folder 7: 8)
      - "The Trip to Glendale," (Folder 7: 9)
      - Untitled biographical sketch of Ivan and Sergei Aksakov (Folder 7: 10)
      - "Volchata,", n.d. (Folder 7: 11)
      - "Kanun Verbnago Voskreseniia," Novaia zaria, 1939 March 31 (Folder 7: 12)
        Holograph and printed copy
    - Miscellany (Folder 7: 13)
  - Chatelain, Mariia (aunt), undated (Folder 7: 14)
  - Demidov (Demidoff), Georgii (cousin), 1946-1963 (Folder 7: 15)
  - Demidov, I. (cousin?), 1946-1963 (Folder 7: 16)
  - Demidov, Igor' Platonovich (uncle)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1931 (Folder 7: 17)
      - Aleksandr, Archbishop, 1934 (Folder 7: 18)
      - Demidov, P. A., 1930 (Folder 7: 19)
      - Gumensky, Catherine, 1945 (Folder 7: 20)
      - Leshetitskii (Leschetizky), T. F., 1931 and undated (Folder 7: 21)
      - Sapon'ko, Angel Osipovich, 1931 (Folder 7: 22)
    - Writings
      - General. (Folder 7: 23)
        Notes and fragments of short stories
      - "Diktator,", n.d. (Folder 7: 24)
        Holograph and typescript
      - "Mary,", n.d. (Folder 7: 25)
      - "Moia mechta,", n.d. (Folder 7: 26)
      - "Persten' i siurtuk Pushkina," Posliedniia novosti, n.d. (Folder 7: 27)
      - "Piatnitsa 13-go iiunia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 28)
      - "Pietush'i besiedy," Posliedniia novosti, n.d. (Folder 7: 29)
      - "Pomieshchichii monastyr',", n.d. (Folder 7: 30)
      - "Posliednii iz mogikan,", n.d. (Folder 7: 31)
      - "Prostaia familiia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 32)
        Typescript
      - "Salomeia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 33)
      - "Sandro Altaev," (Folder 7: 34)
      - "Uzhin v sadu Trokadero,", n.d. (Folder 7: 35)
      - "Velikaia voina i russkaia revoliutsiia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 36)
      - "Zemel'nyia vospominaniia,", n.d. (Folder 7: 37)
      - "Velikaia Noch',"., 1927 December 4 (Folder 7: 38)
      - "Odno iz russkikh chudes," Posliedniia novosti, 1931 January 17 (Folder 7: 39)
      - "Pervyi kadetskii korpus,"., [1931 August] (Folder 7: 40)
        Typescript. Includes several lectures, as well as correspondence
  - Demidova (Demidoff), Sima and Didi (cousin and niece?), 1946-1947 and undated (Folder 7: 41)
  - Gumenskaia, Taisiia Petrovna (mother-in-law), 1922-1947 (Folder 7: 42)
    Includes forwarded letter from Irina Aleksandrova to T. P. Gumenskaia, 1947
  - Gumensky, Dmitrii Veniaminovich (husband)
    - Correspondence
      - Unidentified (Folder 7: 43)
      - Aleksandrova, Irina Aleksandrovna, 1922-1924 (Folder 7: 44)
      - Cherniavskii, Nikolai Filippovich, 1924 (Folder 7: 45)
      - Gumensky, Catherine
        - Incoming, 1921 (Folder 7: 46)
        - Outgoing
          - undated (Folder 7: 47)
          - 1920-1921 (Box-folder 8: 1)
          - 1922 (Folder 8: 2)
          - 1923
            - January-March (Folder 8: 3)
            - April-May (Folder 8: 4)
          - 1924-1925 (Folder 8: 5)
          - 1926-1929 (Box-folder 9: 1)
          - 1932-1942 (Folder 9: 2)
      - Kirillova, O., 1924 (Folder 9: 3)
      - Liubimov, Iurii, 1923 (Folder 9: 4)
      - Ostroumov, Sergei Sergeevich, 1924 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Identity papers (Folder 9: 6)
  - Kovan'ko, Ol'ga Aleksandrovna (sister), 1913-1932 (Folder 9: 7)
  - Liapunov, S. (distant relative), 1923 (Folder 9: 8)
  - Zhuravskaia, S., 1922-1973 and undated (Folder 9: 9)
  - Zhuravskii, Lev S. (nephew) and Aleksandr L. (grandnephew), 1973-1981 (Folder 9: 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1917-1985
  For intra-family correspondence and extrafamilial correspondence of other family members, see FAMILY FILE. For correspondence with Russian war invalids whom she was helping, see SUBJECT FILE/World War, 1914-1918--Veterans--Russia
  This file contains only correspondence of non-family members with Catherine (including letters addressed both to her and Dmitrii Gumensky or Neonila Aristova).
  - General, 1924-1985 (Folder 9: 11)
  - Unidentified, 1917-1949 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - Avinova, Mariia (Avinoff, Marie), n.d. (Folder 10: 2)
  - Bil'kevich, A., 1925 (Folder 10: 3)
  - Dmitrievskii, S., 1932 (Folder 10: 4)
  - Dorofeeva, N., 1927 (Folder 10: 5)
  - Fal'kovskii (Falkovsky), N., 1947 (Folder 10: 6)
  - Fedorovskaia, Ol'ga, 1921-1923 (Folder 10: 7)
  - Gregory, S. M., 1928 (Folder 10: 8)
  - Il'in family, [1941]-1984 (Folder 10: 9)
  - Ivanov, A., 1946 (Folder 10: 10)
  - Kitaeva, Anna, 1924 (Folder 10: 11)
  - Langstroth, Ivan, 1946-1949 (Folder 10: 12)
  - Lebedev, E. and K., 1949 and undated (Folder 10: 13)
  - Lyndall, Dorothy, 1946-1965 and undated (Folder 10: 14)
  - Mashe, L., 1974-1978 (Folder 10: 15)
  - Petrovskii, Mr., n.d. (Folder 10: 16)
  - Poletika (Poletica), E. and O., 1923 (Folder 10: 17)
    Includes clippings and photographs
  - Schmidt, Albert, 1955 and undated (Folder 10: 18)
  - Shcherbatova (Scherbatoff), S., 1953 (Folder 10: 19)
  - Skorodinskii, N., 1949-1952 (Folder 10: 20)
  - Teplova (Teploff), A., 1947 (Folder 10: 21)
  - Vidovskii, Arkadii Arkad'evich, n.d. (Folder 10: 22)
  - Volkov, Georgii, 1940 (Folder 10: 23)
  - von Taube, Baroness, 1921 (Folder 10: 24)
  - Zhadan, Ol'ga, 1949 and undated (Folder 10: 25)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1934-1977
  - General
    - Correspondence with publishers and editors regarding submissions of children's stories, 1934-1940 (Folder 10: 26)
    - Notes, fragments of short stories, and poetry. (Folder 10: 27)
      May include notes by Neonila Aristova and others
  - "Ahmba,", n.d.
    - Notes and fragments (Folder 10: 28)
    - Notes and fragments (Box-folder 11: 1)
    - Typescript (Folder 11: 2)
  - "Fragments from the Note-Book of a Petrograd Student,", n.d. (Folder 11: 3)
    Typescript translation into English of work by an unknown author
  - "Sea Drift,", n.d. (Folder 11: 4)
  - Untitled work on the study of the Russian language, n.d. (Folder 11: 5)
  - "Boots and the Kitten,"., [1939] (Folder 11: 6)
    Typescript. Includes correspondence
  - Untitled account of activities in Europe from 1945 to 1952
    - Background materials. (Folder 11: 7)
      Includes correspondence, 1946, and documents relating to Catherine Gumensky's work in the U.S. Army European Command
    - Daily notes, (fragmentary), 1945-1952 (Folder 11: 8-9)
    - Holograph and typescript (Folder 11: 10)
  - "Russia Today," Apple Valley News, 1977 September 27 (Folder 11: 11)
    Daily notes of trip to U.S.S.R., typescript, and printed copy
- SUBJECT FILE, 1924-1981 (Box 12)
  Clippings, correspondence, notes, writings and other matter
  - Buturlin, Sergei (Folder 12: 1)
  - Dudorov, Boris Petrovich (Folder 12: 2)
  - Russians
    - France (Folder 12: 3)
    - United States (Folder 12: 4)
  - Russkaia Pravoslavnaia Tserkov' (Folder 12: 5)
  - Suniza-Maché, Leo (Folder 12: 6)
  - Tolstoy Foundation. (Folder 12: 7)
    Includes clippings, correspondence, and fundraising materials, 1940-1941
  - World War, --Veterans--Russia., 1914-1918 (Folder 12: 8)
    Correspondence regarding aid to disabled veterans in Bulgaria
  - Young, Ella.
    See also PHOTOGRAPHS
    - Biographical file (Folder 12: 9)
    - Letters to Feodor Gumensky (code name for Catherine?), 1927-1956 (Folder 12: 10)
    - Poetry (Folder 12: 11)
  - Miscellany (Folder 12: 12-13)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, 1910S-1980s (Box 13-16)
- FINANCIAL DOCUMENTS, 1948-1984 (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
- RECIPES, undated (Folder 17: 3)
  Clippings and notes, primarily by N. P. Aristova. May include delicious desserts. Not filmed